Guide to the Carl Van Vechten Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Carl Van Vechten Papers
1866-1986
YCAL MSS 1050
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
182.0
301 boxes + 13 art, 12 broadsides, and 3 broadsides oversize
The Carl Van Vechten Papers includes correspondence, writings, photographs, scrapbooks and albums, and artwork documenting Carl Van Vechten's activities as a writer, photographer, and patron of the arts.
Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964
Conditions Governing Access
Series I. Correspondence, Series II. Writings, Series III. Personal Papers, Series IV. Art, and Series V. Printed Material are open for research. As additional series are processed they will be opened to researchers. For additional information contact the processing archivists.
Box 176 is for research use only, and may not be duplicated.
Boxes 206-209, 213-217, 223: Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Boxes 313-324: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files with the exception of clippings relating to World War I and Edgar Saltus which were too fragile to be duplicated. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 325: Restricted until 2035. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Carl Van Vechten (1880-1964)
Carl Van Vechten was a writer, photographer, collector, and patron of the arts. Born in Cedar Rapids, Iowa, on June 17, 1880, Van Vechten developed an early interest in literature and the fine and performing arts. He attended the University of Chicago, and wrote for several Chicago newspapers before moving to New York City in 1906. Over the next five decades he established himself as a journalist, critic, novelist, photographer, and cultural icon. He wrote music, dance, and theater reviews in New York and Paris for The New York Times and The New York Press, and for magazines and journals including Trend, Vanity Fair, Crisis, New Republic, and Esquire. He authored numerous books including, Music After the Great War (1915), The Tiger in the House (1920), Peter Whiffle: His Life and Works (1922), The Blind-Bow Boy (1923), The Tattooed Countess (1924), Firecrackers (1925), Nigger Heaven (1926), Spider Boy (1928), Parties (1930), and Sacred and Profane Memories (1932), most of which were published by Alfred A. Knopf.
His 1907 marriage to Ann Snyder, a friend since his youth in Cedar Rapids, ended in divorce in 1912. On October 21, 1914 he married Fania Marinoff, an actress who had immigrated to the United States as a child from Russia. They were married for fifty years. A family inheritance received in 1927 provided Van Vechten with the means to support himself and Fania, and freed him to pursue his interests without financial constraints. During the 1920s, Van Vechten was introduced to members of the artistic and cultural movement that would become known as the Harlem Renaissance. He enjoyed frequenting the clubs, restaurants, and salons of Harlem, and he began to develop friendships among members of the Black community. His 1926 novel, Nigger Heaven, was inspired by his visits to Harlem and its residents.
Beginning in the early 1930s Van Vechten devoted much of his time to photography. In his home studio he produced hundreds of photographic portraits of his friends and acquaintances, as well as other world figures whom he photographed by invitation and by recommendations from mutual friends. He and Fania developed a large multicultural network of friends and acquaintances in New York, throughout the United States, and abroad. The Van Vechten apartment became a meeting place for established and developing writers, visual and performing artists, publishers, educators, social activists, and others. Throughout his life Van Vechten developed close friendships with women as well as intimate relationships with men.
As a collector, Van Vechten acquired important collections of books and manuscripts, particularly those relating to African-American arts and literature. In 1941, he established the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts and Letters at Yale University, in honor of the writer and close friend who had died in 1938. In 1947, Van Vechten established the Anna Marble-Pollock Collection of Books about Cats at Yale. He also gave to Yale additional individual books and manuscripts, as well as a large group of his personal papers. He established and/or donated material to collections at other institutions including Fisk University, Howard University, the University of New Mexico, and the New York Public Library (including personal papers dating from 1833 to 1965). Carl Van Vechten died in New York City on December 22, 1964.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Carl Van Vechten and Fania Marinoff, 1941-1971. Additional material acquired through gifts and purchases is noted in folder-level acquisition notes.
Scope and Contents
The Carl Van Vechten Papers include correspondence, writings, photographs, scrapbooks and albums, ephemera, and artwork documenting Carl Van Vechten's activities as a writer, photographer and patron of the arts. The papers date from 1866 to 1986, and include early documents and printed items collected by Van Vechten, and material about Van Vechten and Marinoff published posthumously.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1900-1971. II. Writings, 1913-1966. Series III. Personal Papers, 1879-1971. Series IV. Art, 1866-1964. V. Printed Material, 1871-1986.
Related Materials
Carl Van Vechten Papers Relating to African American Arts and Letters (JWJ MSS 1050). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Carl Van Vechten Papers. New York Public Library, New York, New York.
Fania Marinoff (1890-1971)
Fania Marinoff, was born in Odessa, Russia on March 20, 1890, and came to the United States as a child with her family in the mid-1890s. After her family settled in Boston, Fania moved with her older brothers to Denver, Colorado. She began her stage career as a child in Denver, and toured with a stock company before establishing a career in New York City. She married Carl Van Vechten in 1914. Her performance as Ariel in the tercentenary revival of The Tempest in 1916 was highly praised. On Broadway she acted in productions including Arms and the Man (1915), The Streets of New York (1931), The Pillars of Society (1931), and Antony and Cleopatra (1937). She also performed in The Skin of Our Teeth at the Westport Country Playhouse in 1948. Marinoff appeared in early films including The Unsuspected Isles (1915), The Rise of Jenny Cushing (1917), and Life's Whirlpool (1917), and performed on radio broadcasts and various special stage performances. She performed less frequently after 1940, but maintained friendships with fellow actors, directors, and managers, with whom she corresponded throughout her life. Fania Marinoff died in Englewood, New Jersey on November 16, 1971.
Artists; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Photographers -- United States; Paintings (visual works); Photographs; Scrapbooks; Artists; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographers -- United States -- 20th Century; LGBTQ resource; Angus, Donald; Banks, Richard, 1929-; Cabell, James Branch, 1879-1958; Ewing, Max; Ficke, Arthur Davison, 1883-1945; Hergesheimer, Joseph, 1880-1954; Hurst, Fannie, 1889-1968; Kellner, Bruce, 1930-; Kenton, Edna, 1876-1954; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984; Knopf, Blanche W., 1894-1966; Lueders, Edward, 1923-; Luhan, Mabel Dodge, 1879-1962; Lutz, Mark, 1901-1969; Marble-Pollock, Anna; Marinoff, Fania, 1890-1971; O'Neill, Carlotta; Perper, Leo; Pollock, Helen Channing; Priebe, Karl J., 1914-1976; Pringle, Aileen, 1895-1989; Purdy, James, 1914-2009; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946; Stettheimer, Florine, 1871-1944; Taylor, Prentiss, 1907-1991; Toklas, Alice B., 1877-1967; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; Vanderbilt, Gloria, 1924-; New York Public Library; Yale University
- Correspondence, 1907-1971; Series I; 79.8; 183 boxes
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: A-Z Correspondence; Copies of Correspondence from Other Manuscript Repositories; and Greeting Cards. A-Z Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and chronologically within files. Correspondents represented by fewer than three letters are filed in "Letter" general files. Copies of Correspondence from Other Manuscript Repositories is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Greeting Cards include Holiday Cards, which are arranged chronologically, and Cat-themed cards, arranged by size.
  At some point in the past, library staff numbered each incoming letter from some correspondents in pencil. Where the numbering of each letter did not match the chronological ordering of the letters, current staff arranged them chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence, documents Carl Van Vechten's activities as a writer, critic, photographer, collector, and supporter of the arts from the 1910s through his death in 1964. The series includes letters from and about friends, acquaintances, and business contacts who made up a social circle that included artists, writers and publishers, actors, directors, composers, musicians and singers, dancers, social activists, and others. Van Vechten's correspondence from and about African Americans may be found in the Carl Van Vechten Papers Relating to African American Arts and Letters (JWJ MSS 1050). The Carl Van Vechten Papers held by the New York Public Library contain the bulk of correspondence documenting his writing career, marriages, and family.
  The correspondence consists chiefly of incoming letters. When present, Van Vechten's drafts, carbon copies, and original letters to correspondents are interfiled with incoming letters. Original letters from Van Vechten were acquired directly from the correspondent or from his or her heirs, who are noted when known. Enclosures often include newspaper and magazine clippings, performance programs, advertisements, invitations, photographs, etc. Significant enclosures and third-party letters are described in folder-level scope and content notes. Letters to Fania Marinoff are interfiled with those to Van Vechten; folder-level scope and content notes indicate when an individual's correspondence was sent only to Fania (FM).
  The series includes extensive correspondence with friends Robert Downing, Bruce Kellner, Edna Kenton, Alfred and Blanche Knopf, Hugh Laing, Mabel Dodge Luhan, Mark Lutz, Leo and Kathleen Perper, Channing Pollock, Anna Marble-Pollock, Helen Channing Pollock, Karl Priebe, Aileen Pringle, James Purdy, Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas, and Prentiss Taylor. The letters, in some cases written daily, relate personal and professional activities as well as news and gossip, and often include photographs, newspaper and magazine clippings, performance programs, and other ephemera.
  Correspondence between Van Vechten and Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas dates from 1913 to 1967, and includes exchanges regarding activities, publications, travels, and domestic life. As executor of Stein's literary estate, Van Vechten maintained files of correspondence regarding permissions to publish and perform Stein's works. Most of these files immediately follow the Stein correspondence; others are filed by the name of permission seeker in the full listing. Third-party correspondence also includes letters from mutual friends enclosed with Stein's letters, and letters from American servicemen and others who met Stein and Toklas in France and reported back to Van Vechten. Following Stein's death Alice Toklas corresponded with Van Vechten regarding requests for permission to publish Stein's works, Toklas's own publications, and her health and welfare.
  Van Vechten's correspondence also documents his relationships with artists Dorothy Brett, Paul Cadmus, Miguel Covarrubias, Philip Grausman, Georgia O'Keeffe, and Florine Stettheimer; writers William Rose Benét, Karen Blixen, Witter Bynner, James Branch Cabell, Max Ewing, Arthur Davison Ficke, Lillian Hellman, Joseph Hergesheimer, Fannie Hurst, H.L. Mencken, Henry Miller, Anaïs Nin, Eugene O'Neill (and his wife Carlotta Monterey O'Neill) and Hunter Stagg; actors/directors Daniel Frohman, Lillian Gish, Helen Hayes, Alfred Lunt and Lynn Fontanne, Lawrence Langner, Armina Marshall, Mary Martin, Zachary Scott and Anna May Wong; musicians and composers Aaron Copland, Mary Garden, and Virgil Thomson; dancers and choreographers Agnes De Mille, Alicia Markova, Ted Shawn and Antony Tudor. Correspondence relating to the making of portrait photographs by Van Vechten include thank-you notes and requests for additional copies of photographs from the sitters.
  Van Vechten's donations of books, manuscripts, and photographs to the Museum of the City of New York, New York Public Library, the University of New Mexico, Yale University, and other institutions and individuals are documented by letters, gift acknowledgements, lists, and other material. Correspondence relating to Van Vechten's World War II activities as a volunteer for the American Theatre Wing's Stage Door Canteen include administrative memos and letters from servicemen and fellow volunteers, as well as documents including mailing addresses, tickets, and other ephemera.
  Van Vechten family correspondence includes cards and letters from Van Vechten's father, Charles Duane Van Vechten; brother Ralph Van Vechten; nephew, Van Vechten Shaffer and his wife Angevine; niece Duane Van Vechten; and an extended family member, Walter Burr Van Vechten.
  Letters to Fania Marinoff chiefly relate to her acting career, including letters from playwrights, producers and directors; fellow actors; and notes and telegrams of congratulations from friends and fans. Fania Marinoff's family is represented by letters from her brother, Jacob (Jack) Marinoff and his wife Esther; nephew Nathan Marinoff and his wife Esther; brother Louis Marinoff; nephew David and his wife Rosemary; and nephew Oscar Marinoff and his wife Kate. A single letter from her father Mayer Marinoff, and letters from miscellaneous extended family members are filed under Marinoff family members. A 1901 letter from F. W. Evans to Fania's brother Michael Marinoff, and a 1916 letter from Mrs. A. B. Morgan to Fania, provide insight into Fania's youth in Denver, Colorado. Correspondence between Van Vechten and Marinoff consists of a few letters, and numerous birthday and holiday greeting cards, both commercial and hand-made.
  - A-Z Correspondence
    - "A" General, 1914-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Abbott, Berenice, 1910–1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Abdullah, Achmed, 1920; 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Letters to FM
    - Aberconway, Christabel Mary Melville Macnaghten McLaren, Baroness
      Includes photographs, clippings, performance programs, and third-party correspondence relating to Aberconway's interests in cats, literature, and the arts
      - 1949–1952 (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
      - Dust Jacket, undated (Box 181 (Oversize), Folder 2300)
        Dust jacket for Your Siamese Cat by Hettie Gray Baker, previously enclosed with 1951 November 29 letter from Aberconway to CVV
      - 1953–1965 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
        Includes Mr. Korah and the Monster by Christabel Aberconway and Rex Whistler (illustrator), printed by Herbert Fitch & Co. Ltd., London [195?]
    - Abercrombie, Gertrude, 1950–1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Academy of Arts and Letters
      Related Materials
      See: National Institute of Arts and Letters
    - Acosta, Mercedes de, 1943–1964 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Acton, Harold, 1927–1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Includes a letter of introduction for S. H. Chen from Acton to CVV, with letter from Chen to CVV (1941)
    - Actors' Equity Association, 1918–1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Actors' Fund of America, 1930–1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Adamic, Louis, 1937–1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Adams, Diana, 1954–1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Adler, Celia, 1920 October 26 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Letter to FM
    - Adler, Elmer, 1934–1962 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - After Dinner Opera Company, 1942; 1956 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Ailes, Edgar H., 1943–1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Includes original letters to Ailes from CVV, and correspondence with the Yale University Library regarding Ailes's gift of Max Ewing letters
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift of Edgar H. Ailes, 1966-1967
    - Alastair, 1924–1932 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Albee, Edward, 1961–1964 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Albright Art Gallery, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Alexander, Raymond Pace, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc.
      See also: Knopf, Blanche; Knopf, Alfred A.
      - 1919–1969 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
        Includes correspondence with various staff regarding writings by CVV and others
      - Contract, 1921 (Box 181 (Oversize), Folder 2301)
        CVV contract with Knopf for Peter Whiffle
    - Allgood, Sara, 1913–1942 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1934–1967 (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
      Includes correspondence with the National Institute of Arts and Letters
    - American Academy of Dramatic Arts, 1962–1963 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - American Caravan, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - American Center of P.E.N., 1923; 1929 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - American Magazine, 1934; 1937 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - American Publishing Company, 1916 April 24 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - American Shakespeare Festival Theatre and Academy, 1963; 1968; undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
      See also: Theatre Guild
    - American Theatre Wing
      - 1943–1964 (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
      - Club for Merchant Seamen, 1942–1945 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Stage Door Canteen
        - 1942-1946, undated (Box 4, Folder 41-45)
        - Architectural drawing, 1945 (Box 182 (Oversize), Folder 2329)
          Architectural drawing for the Stage Door Canteen by Emeline Clark Roche
        - Letters from servicemen, 1943-1946, undated (Box 4, Folder 46-49)
          Includes photographs of servicemen by CVV and others
        - Notes, mailing addresses, and ephemera, 1943; undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
        - Notes regarding photographs and addresses of models, circa 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 51)
        - Tea dances for servicemen and women, 1944-1946, undated (Box 5, Folder 52-55)
          Includes tickets, notes, and mailing addresses
    - Ames, Richard Sheridan, 1951–1952 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Ames, Winthrop, 1916; 1926 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Anderson, Chris, 1951–1952 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Anderson, Judith, 1937-1964, undated (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Anderson, Margaret, 1951–1963 (Box 5, Folder 60)
      Photograph of Anderson and Solita Solano enclosed with letter to CVV (1963)
    - Anderson, Sherwood, 1932–1960 (Box 5, Folder 61)
      Includes form letter on National Committee for the Defense of Political Prisoners letterhead with typescript mimeograph statement, "Protest to the President" (1932); letters from Eleanor Anderson (1946, 1961); third-party letters regarding photographs of Anderso, and the publication of Anderson's letters
    - Andre, Mary Z., 1929; 1931 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Andrews, Ann
      - 1926–1959 (Box 5, Folder 63-64)
      - 1960-1964, undated (Box 6, Folder 65-66)
    - Andrews, Wayne, 1937–1938 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - Andrewski, Gene, 1958–1959 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Angus, Donald
      See also: Papp, Joseph
      - 1920–1963 (Box 6, Folder 69-74)
      - 1964-1971, undated (Box 7, Folder 75-76)
        Includes photograph of Angus and his dog, Coco (undated)
    - Ann Watkins, Inc., 1923–1946 (Box 7, Folder 77)
      Includes correspondence signed by Ann Watkins, Margot Johnson, and Jean Macy
    - Anspacher, Louis Kaufman, 1917–1918 (Box 7, Folder 78)
    - Arden, Edwin, 1918 February 2 (Box 7, Folder 79)
    - Arden, Elsie, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 80)
    - Arensberg, Walter, 1915–1917 (Box 7, Folder 81)
    - Arenstein, Yetta, 1958-1965, undated (Box 7, Folder 82-84)
      Includes correspondence signed by Nancy Ferguson
    - Argo, Leif, 1955-1957, undated (Box 7, Folder 85)
      Includes photograph of Argo and unidentified woman at Chateau Madrid (undated)
    - Arlen, Howard, 1957, 1964, undated (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - Armitage, Merle, 1937–1938 (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - Askew, R. Kirk (Ralph Kirk), 1934–1965 (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - Atherton, Gertrude Franklin Horn
      - 1915–1939 (Box 7, Folder 89-90)
      - 1940-1948, undated (Box 8, Folder 91)
      - Magazine clipping, 1946 November 11 (Box 181 (Oversize), Folder 2302)
        Clipping of article on Gertrude Atherton from Life magazine
    - Atkinson, Brooks, 1939-1970, undated (Box 8, Folder 92-94)
      Includes ephemera relating to events honoring Atkinson (1958, 1960); correspondence from Atkinson's wife, Oriana Atkinson
    - Atlantic Monthly, 1916–1951 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - Atlantic Monthly Press, 1951–1959 (Box 8, Folder 96)
    - Aug, Edna
      - 1924–1932 (Box 8, Folder 97-99)
      - 1933–1939 (Box 9, Folder 100-104)
    - Auslander, Joseph, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 105)
    - Austin, Arthur Everett, 1931–1958 (Box 9, Folder 106)
    - Authors' League of America, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 107)
    - Avakian, George, 1951–1956 (Box 9, Folder 108)
    - Avedon, Richard, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 109)
    - Avnet, Nan, 1971 June 10 (Box 9, Folder 110)
      Letter to FM written on behalf of Avnet by her sister, Ethel Kaplan
    - Ayres, Gerald, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 111)
    - "B" General, 1908-1966, undated (Box 10, Folder 112-119)
    - Babb, James T. (James Tinkham), 1948–1965 (Box 10, Folder 120)
      Includes letters from Babb's wife, Peg Babb
    - Bachardy, Don, 1954; 1964 (Box 10, Folder 121)
    - Baida, Ruth, 1958–1964 (Box 10, Folder 122)
    - Baker, Martha Susan, 1906–1938 (Box 10, Folder 123)
      Includes letters from Susan S. Baker and The Art Institute of Chicago
    - Baldwin, Charles C. (Charles Crittenton), 1924 (Box 11, Folder 124)
    - Bankhead, Tallulah, 1920–1952 (Box 11, Folder 125)
    - Banks, Danny, 1963–1964 (Box 11, Folder 126)
    - Banks, Richard
      - 1951–1963 (Box 11, Folder 127-133)
        Includes typescript reveiws by Banks of CVV's books Firecrackers and Interpreters and Interpretations (1952)
      - Piano scores, 1954 (Box 181 (Oversize), Folder 2303)
        Piano scores by Banks, copies, of "A Sonatina Followed by Another" (based on poem by Gertrude Stein) and "Clay Angels," previously enclosed with Banks's letter of 1954 July 29
      - Piano score, [1960 June 17] (Box 181 (Oversize), Folder 2304)
        Piano score, copy, "A Birthday Song for Carl Van Vechten" (poem by Florine Stettheimer), previously enclosed with Banks's letter of [1960 June 17?]
      - 1964-1973, undated (Box 12, Folder 134-135)
        Includes card to CVV (undated) containing six facsimile Confederate States of America currency bills
    - Banyon Press
      Includes correspondence with Claude Fredericks (Zawy) and Milton Saul (Mup)
      - 1947–1949 (Box 12, Folder 136-142)
        Includes photograph of Milton Saul, and original photographic postcards (circa 1890) of Pawlet, Vermont (1948)
      - 1950-1951, undated (Box 13, Folder 143)
    - Bara, Theda, 1939; 1952 (Box 13, Folder 144)
    - Bardwell, Steve, 1968 May 6 (Box 13, Folder 145)
    - Bardwell, Vivian, 1956–1965 (Box 13, Folder 146)
    - Barkentin, Marjorie, 1944–1961 (Box 13, Folder 147)
    - Barnes, Albert C. (Albert Coombs), 1933–1960 (Box 13, Folder 148-150)